Jeeoff, thanks a lot for doing this.
>> Uh, great to be with you.
>> Where does it go from here? The war in
Iran.
You know, we always talk about the fork
in the road. We're really we're really
at a decisive moment. Uh there's an
off-ramp.
It's definitely definitely definitely
the one that we should be taking.
We should be avoiding a return to
outright bombing to uh uh renewed uh
military uh action.
That's a very real possibility.
And the other possibility in my view is
pretty much an uncontrolled uh
escalation into uh full-blown war. Uh
that would become a regional war and
that could become a world war. Um I
think we're really at that moment right
now. Maybe that uh sounds naive because
why not next week? Why not the week
after? Why not the week after? Uh but
the problem is that we're not in a
stable situation where we can choose one
or the other. We're in an unstable
situation as we speak. Uh the world
economy is reeling. It's reeling because
uh as everybody has learned in their
geography in the last uh few weeks, the
straight of Hormuz is closed.
as long as it's closed uh it means that
there's a worldwide economic crisis
building. So time is not uh permissive
right now. We can't say well we'll
decide in another month. We'll see how
things go. We'll negotiate and see what
happens. Right now there is a an ongoing
building global serious economic crisis
and that is because uh a uh narrow
stretch of water through which uh comes
a an enormous
extremely important strategic flow of
resources. oil and gas obviously, but
also fertilizers and petrochemicals and
uh many many other key commodities,
aluminum and others is closed.
To simply open it is fine. That's
basically what the off-ramp uh would
allow. It would be the right answer.
uh it would not solve
any of the underlying issues that uh led
to this uh and it would not solve any of
the stated objectives of the United
States, much less Israel. I don't
believe those objectives were valid and
therefore I don't think that they should
be the basis of a decision to take or to
not take that exit ramp. But the point
is there's a way out of this thing that
would avoid
uh the escalation to something quite
different. So what is that other path?
The other path is well we're in this uh
unstable situation. in the world economy
is reeling because of the straight of
hormones being closed and we have to do
something about it. We can't just sit
there for weeks or months and we refuse
to just allow it to reopen and not have
those goals met. So, uh Trump and his
partner in this Netanyahu uh might say
the only thing we can do is make the
maximal threat and if that threat uh
does not lead to Iran conceding, then we
have to follow through not with more
time and waiting because of this
unstable situation, but we have to
return to massive bombing this time even
more. And what we can suspect on that
alternative is that the Iranians will of
course strike back and strike back very
hard and very rapidly.
And what we have all learned also since
February 28th, since the start of this
war, is that the entire Gulf region is
exposed to missile fire from Iran as is
in fact because we also have come to
understand that the anti-missile
defenses are permeable uh limited uh
even depleted in many areas. But we know
that the desalination plants in the Gulf
region, the oil and the gas fields, uh
the port facilities are not protected
systematically and comprehensively
against Iranian attacks.
and Iran would completely totally
understandably
respond to what Trump has repeatedly
threatened which is the destruction of
Iran. So if we don't take the exit ramp,
I personally don't see
anything realistic less than an allout
war.
And while I'm an economist,
simple economist, not a military
analyst,
uh having watched this for decades and
tried to understand from the military
analysts, I think it would be but a few
weeks before a very very large part of
the infrastructure of the region was
destroyed
>> in Iran and in the Gulf and a lot in
Israel as well. And the result of that
would not be uh peace followed by some
easy recovery. It would be a global
calamity brought upon us in a few short
weeks. So to return to uh the basic
question,
Trump could say, "We're not going to go
to disaster. We just pull back." That's
the right answer.
If he says instead, uh, we can't wait
any longer. We're going to attack, I
believe we will see a different world
four weeks from now. uh a world uh that
is uh profoundly
damaged,
the world economy in crisis, the
possibility of escalation to a full
world war. And I don't think I'm being
hyperbolic
uh or naive to say that we are at that
fork in the road right now. The problem
once again is that the right thing to do
is not uh a political victory for Trump.
Uh it's not and it's an outright loss
from Netanyahu.
Personally, I don't care about either of
those. I don't think the individual
fates of two politicians should
determine the fate of the world because
I don't think that the objectives of
Trump and Netanyahu going into this made
any sense at all. They weren't
objectives that I supported or support
today or that I believe uh believed uh
on February 28th were within reach or
that I believe today are within reach.
So, the fact that the off-ramp is not a
success story
doesn't bother me at all. It's the right
way to save the world. And it's
the responsibility of um grown-ups uh to
try to save the world. uh not to save
face, not to double down on failed
gambles, uh not to engage in reckless
escapades,
and that's why the off-ramp is is the
right thing to do. Uh it requires uh
grown-up behavior.
I don't associate that term with these
two leaders very easily, unfortunately.
So, I'm not extremely optimistic about
what's going to happen.
>> So, the weather is warming, which means
grilling is here, and you're probably
already thinking about your first
backyard barbecue of the year. What
should you put on the barbecue? We
recommend Good Ranchers. We've been
using Good Ranchers for a while, and the
difference is obvious. They partner with
local American farmers and ranchers to
deliver 100% American meat right to your
door. Pasture-raised, no antibiotics, no
added hormones, and excellent quality
and taste.
Good Ranchers also just launched their
new custom boxes. So instead of choosing
a predetermined list of meat choices,
you can build your own box with the cuts
that you want. Steaks for grilling,
chicken for weekn night dinner, whatever
you decide. You start your plan, you get
to choose a free meat that included with
every order at no additional cost. Plus,
with the code Tucker, you get $25 off
your first order. That's free meat with
every order and 25 bucks off your first
order. Use the code Tucker to get that.
Goodranchers.com.
American meat delivered and it's
excellent. They would I agree with every
word you've said, but in fairness, they
would have to swallow a lot to walk this
back because it would mean that Iran is
more powerful now in effect than it was
before the war started at the end of
February. Correct. We would have to
acknowledge they control the strait and
you know 20% of the world's energy and
30% of its fertilizer. Iran controls
that supply chain.
That's essentially correct. Uh except
for uh a couple of important
considerations.
One is uh that um Iran has suffered very
heavily uh by this attack. Uh let's
start by recalling the 160 school girls
killed on the first day by uh apparently
Palunteer's uh AI system. Uh well, like
we find out every day when we're looking
at our screen, uh this is an AI. It can
make mistakes. Uh well, apparently uh uh
Palunteer's mistake was to kill 160
innocent school girls. Uh this is not
definitively known, but it's what is
being widely reported. So, we will
perhaps someday find out what really
happened. Iran has lost thousands of
people. Iran has been devastated. Tens
of billions of dollars of uh damages
that will take years and years basically
to recover. For me as a development
economist whose whole career uh over
half a century is to try to build
things. I don't like to see things
knocked down this way. the mind
mindlessness of it, the cruelty of it,
the uh brazen destruction, the
glorification of this violence by
Hegathth and others uh I find completely
completely totally repulsive.
So uh first Iran has suffered a lot.
There's no glory uh in the offramp.
There's just uh continued bereiement
uh people still being buried. uh deaths,
deprivation,
uh suffering. So no joy and therefore uh
no in my view not a humiliation.
Second,
it's weird to say and I'm sure many
people will uh object to what I'm about
to say or not understand it or think I
don't know what I'm talking about, but I
do.
The Iranian people
are really very civilized. They have
wanted to negotiate for years. All of
this depiction of the evil of Iran that
we have been uh played to since 1979
also mistakes uh the reality in a
fundamental way. And so when you say
that Iran would control the straits,
actually they would not control it in a
malevolent way that Americans would be
led to expect by hearing that this is
the most evil of evil empires. That's
what we've been told for decades, that
this is the axis of evil, that this is
the heart of evil. uh Netanyahu uh uh
said uh that they wanted to annihilate
us and so forth. This is not correct at
all. It is our
non-stop official propaganda narrative.
uh if you go to Iran, which I have been
very lucky to do, if you speak to
Iranians, which I do frequently and have
done for
a very long time, the official narrative
that
Iran is so evil that we can't leave it
in control of the straight of Hormuz
just gets everything wrong to begin
with. And maybe I'll just say one quick
historical
word about this. Where does this hatred
and venom come from? Uh
with respect to the United States, it's
very simple.
In 1953,
Iran was a parliamentary democracy. Uh
Iran had not invaded or attacked another
country for a century and a half. This
was a peaceful country. Uh it had been
invaded several times. Uh but it was a
democracy that didn't threaten anybody,
didn't want to threaten anybody, hadn't
threatened anybody, hadn't invaded uh
any place actually since the 1790s in a
in in a brawl over who controlled Bazra.
So in other words, very esoteric things
from uh the 1790s. But since then, Iran
had been bothered but had not bothered
anybody else. And in 1953,
the Iranian prime minister
elected uh respected uh prime minister
Mosedc had the audacity
to say the uh
the thing never to be said by this
region which is I think the oil under
our ground is Iranian not British. uh
and uh when he uttered that thought uh
that maybe Iran's oil belonged to Iran
immediately the British Empire in the
form of MI6 came to the new ascendant
American Empire in the guise of the CIA
and said um we got to overthrow this guy
which of course they did successfully.
They made what today we would call a
color revolution. They stirred up
protests in the streets. They stirred up
unrest and Mosedc was chased from power.
And the United States installed what the
Persian Empire would have called a
satrappy. Uh meaning that Iran became a
kind of province of the American Empire
under ultimately CIA rule. And we put
the sha of Iran uh as the face of that
empire and the police organization Savak
uh as the enforcers of that empire. That
lasted 26 years. In 1979, as the sha of
Iran was dying of cancer, the people uh
led a revolution, an uprising uh and uh
threw out Savak and the CIA uh and uh
and the sha and that's when uh uh Iran
had its Islamic revolution and put in a
the government that is government until
today. The United States hated that.
When you're an empire as we are, when
you have protectorates, when you have uh
places where you have your military, and
in the case of Iran, uh when your major
oil companies have investments there
that suddenly are lost because what was
stolen from Iran is now taken back by
Iran. Uh that led to uh a reputational
question. We need to bring Iran back
under our control because we're an
empire. If we're too weak visav any
piece of our empire, it damages our
reputation anywhere. We need to punish
these people for what they've done. And
there was the hostage taking by uh the
uh youth
radical groups who said we're doing this
because we want the sha to be brought
back here uh to uh um face uh a trial in
Iran for the crimes of the police state
over the last 23 years. And the United
States had taken in the sha in a very
unwise decision by President Carter uh
in 1979 for medical treatment uh knowing
that suspecting it was going to lead to
this kind of eruption. They demanded
reparations. They demanded an apology.
They demanded an end to the US uh
subversion of Iran. All pretty
reasonable actually. But of course it
became the cause of the United States in
1979. and another humiliation for
America which an empire never tolerates.
An empire needs to repay any kind of
loss of face with uh some kind of
extreme punishment not only to get that
particular recalcitrant place under
control but to signal to all the rest of
the empire don't you dare try this. So
from 1980 onward, the US has been at war
with Iran in various ways. In 1980
onward, we paid, we armed, we supplied.
Saddam Hussein
to invade Iran. Uh pretty sorted deal.
Saddam Hussein used uh poison gas uh
with American knowledge at the minimum
and according to some uh testimonies,
American active support, but we engaged
in a war in Iran through a proxy through
Iraq from the very start uh of uh this
1979 government. Donald Trump already
back in 1980
said we have to overthrow this
government. So when Trump gives his
explanations for the current war, he
says, "Oh, nuclear or this or that."
This is uh these are convenient
uh current explanations for something
that has been on his mind for 46 years
as well because the American Empire
suffered a slight uh a country got out
from under American CIA control which
you don't allow to happen. And from
1980, it's been nonstop
war. It's been an economic war. what our
Treasury Secretary, who I increasingly
regard to be a thug, basically not a
Treasury Secretary, but someone who
delights and gloats in crushing other
economies by using financial means or
trade sanctions or uh financial
blockages and delights in it. uh
explained uh in Davos this year in a Fox
News interview uh with Maria Barto Romo
that our state craft destroyed the
Iranian economy last year. Well, we've
been doing that kind of statecraft. What
a horrible Orwellian term for destroying
another country's economy. We've been
doing that for decades.
>> Well, there's been a lot of noise in the
news lately, but none of it matters if
you can't hear it. And there's no shame
in that. It happens to millions of
people every year. If you shoot a lot,
you know the feeling. Our friends at
Audient can change your life. Audient
offers FDA compliant hearing aids for as
low as $98. No prescription, no doctor's
visit required, available at over 10,000
retailers nationwide, including Walmart
and Walgreens. Over 1.5 million
Americans already use Audian, and it's
changed their lives. No more squinting
and struggling to hear as people try to
talk to you. Audient helps you reconnect
to the world. and more important to
other people who are the key to life.
Visit heretucker.com that's hereh
artucker.com or call 18004532916
to learn more about how Audian can help
you or someone you love hear better.
It's essential healthcare hearing and
it's now accessible and affordable.
That's the system should have done all
along. And we have been engaged in
assassinations of Iranian leaders. We
have been engaged in uh blowing up uh
their nuclear facilities even when uh
they have been pleading let's have an
agreement that puts us under strict
supervision of the international atomic
energy agency. We've been using what's
called hybrid warfare, every possible
means of subversion, of economic
warfare, of direct military action, of
covert operations. Donald Trump
confirmed that in the protests last
year, the US sent weapons to the
protesters. That's not a protest. That's
an insurrection we were creating. Uh
that did not work. But the point I'm
making is that we portray Iran as evil
because it did something unacceptable to
the United States that doesn't involve
nuclear weapons or any of the specific
issues or Hezbollah or Hamas. It goes
back to 1979.
They escaped from the American Empire.
They escaped from CIA control. That's
not allowed. That's simply what you're
not supposed to to do. And uh this war
has been going on with various pretexts,
various explanations since then.
>> May ask you if I could just say one more
thing, Tucker. Um
>> Trump's main argument
has been in the last uh uh months, I
will stop them from having a nuclear
weapon. Of
course, anyone that knows the history of
this knows that this is Orwell to the
nth power. By that, I mean such bizarre
propaganda,
you don't quite even know where to
start. The reason is that the Iranians
have not pursued a nuclear weapon. Our
own intelligence agencies have said that
repeatedly.
What they have pursued though is a
treaty
with the UN Security Council to confirm
that to put them under strict monitoring
under the nuclear non-prololiferation
treaty but in return for ending the US
economic warfare on Iran. What Iran has
wanted for 15 years is you supervise us,
you control us. Fine, but lift your
sanctions. Let us breathe. Let us have a
normal economy. Let us trade. And
President Obama.
And by the way, one other thing, let us
have our own money back because the
United States has confiscated tens of
billions of dollars of Iran's money.
Iran's money, not our money. Because we
do that as an empire. We freeze the
money of other countries. We sometimes
just overtly take it and use it for
something else. It's rather obnoxious to
my point of view and rather
self-defeating in the long term for the
United States to have the reputation
that it just steals other people's
fiscal uh and financial resources. But
we did that with Iran. So what Iran has
wanted is diplomacy.
And I come back again, they're nice
people. They're diplomats. And I
sometimes tell them, you don't even know
who you're dealing with here, how nasty
this is, how difficult this is. Uh, no,
no, no. We want an agreement, Professor
Saxs. Do you know who we might speak to
about uh negotiations and so forth? very
civilized, very nice people. In 2015,
such an agreement was reached, the joint
comprehensive plan of action, the JCPOA.
It was reached not only with the United
States, but with Britain, with France,
with Russia, with China, and with
Germany. The five permanent members of
the UN Security Council plus Germany
called 5+ 1. Then it went to the UN
Security Council where it was
unanimously backed.
Then came the Zionist lobby in the
United States. Oh no, you can't have an
agreement with Iran. They're the evil
empire. You can't do this. Uh and so
when Trump was elected in the first
term, he ripped up the JCPOA.
This is the approach that you don't want
them to have a nuclear weapon when you
had the control. No, this is the
opposite. This is we need to change the
regime because they humiliated the
United States by escaping from our
empire.
We tried to defeat them in many ways,
but they stood up to it. We need to
defeat them.
There's an Israeli version which is not
exactly the same. And the Israeli
version is we need to have absolute
control over the Middle East so that we
can pursue our greater Israel agenda.
This is not exactly the US cause, but
there are people in the US that are the
backers of that distinct cause. That's
not Israel saying you escaped from the
American Empire. That's Israel saying,
"We control almost all of the Middle
East militarily, but Iran we don't yet
control." So that's the last big prize.
And that's the other part of this agenda
right now. And why Israel is even more
against the off-ramp than the United
States. Trump is against the off-ramp
because he can't declare victory because
he would lose face because it would be
he'd face pressure groups because there
are uh we we have the Israel or the
Zionist lobby I would I would call it uh
in the United States. For Israel, the
issue is
uh somewhat distinct, but Israel's main
issue is that it wants complete
military dominance of West Asia and uh
the the Middle East and even into the
Horn of Africa and North Africa. And it
almost has that uh not that it uh can
easily control all of the territory. No,
by no means, but it is able to act with
impunity. It's able to invade
Lebanon. It's able to occupy Syria. It's
able to overthrow other countries
governments and that's what it wants.
But it faces an obstacle and the
obstacle is Iran. So most people don't
wake up in the morning and decide to
feel horrible, exhausted, foggy,
disconnected from themselves. But it
does happen and it happens slowly.
You're working hard, you're showing up,
and then your energy disappears by
midday. Your focus is dull. Your weight
won't move. A lot of people are told
that's just getting old. That's what it
is. But that's not actually true.
For many men and women, these are not
personal failures. They are signals tied
to your metabolism, your hormones, and
nutrient imbalances that go undetected
for years. You don't even know you're
deficient. And that's why we're happy to
partner with Joy and Bloss, a company
that was built for people who are all
done guessing and ready to figure out
what exactly is going on. And that
starts with comprehensive lab work and a
one-on-one consultation with a licensed
clinician. An actual human being
explains what's happening inside you and
builds a personalized plan which
includes hormone optimization, peptide
therapy, targeted supplements. So don't
settle. Go to joinblo.com/tucker.
Use the code Tucker for 50% off your lab
work and 20% off all supplements. That's
joy and bloss.com/tucker.
Use the code Tucker. 50% off labs, 20%
off supplements. Join Blok. Get your
edge back.
Israel 30 years ago this year when
Netanyahu first became prime minister uh
adopted a strategy that was explained in
a public paper called the clean break
strategy. And the clean break strategy
said we will never accept we being our
new government never accept a state of
Palestine. We will occupy all of what
had been the British Palestine, British
mandatory Palestine. In other words,
we'll control Gaza. We'll control the
West Bank. We'll control all of
Jerusalem. And we may control other
places as well. We'll never do that, but
we'll face resistance uh when we make
that claim and hold on to this
territory. We'll definitely face
resistance. We'll definitely face
resistance of militant groups. But what
Netanyahu and his colleagues in the
United States said was rather than
fighting those militant groups directly,
we need to bring down the governments in
the Middle East and West Asia that
support those groups. And that is what's
called the clean break strategy. The
clean break was the clean break from the
peace accords, from the land for peace
idea that Israel would return to its
borders. there would be a Palestinian
state in return for peace. That's what
international law says. But what Israel
says is we're never returning. We're
there's never going to be a state of
Palestine.
In fact, we're going to have what we
call greater Israel, which is all of
Palestine, including Gaza, West Bank,
East Jerusalem,
legal Israel, but also
expanded parts of the region. And when
you interviewed uh Ambassador Huckabe,
the US ambassador to Israel, he put it
very clearly uh that the great zealots,
including Huckabe. And many of the
Israeli leaders view greater Israel as
control from a big slice of Egypt uh all
the way to Iraq. uh from uh what is
taken to be even a biblical uh gift of
God to uh uh the uh ancient Israelites
uh from the river of Egypt to the great
river of Mesopotamia meaning uh the
Euphrates River. So Israel wants
military dominance.
The clean break idea was
when we aim for that we'll find
resistance. We don't fight and
extinguish the militant groups because
we can't. We have to fight the
governments that back them. And that's
where the idea of perpetual war in the
Middle East came from. Or not perpetual
war, but actually specifically seven
wars uh were designated that would
overthrow governments supporting
Palestinian militancy. And those
governments were, Libya,
Sudan, Somalia,
Lebanon,
Syria,
Iraq, and Iran.
And we've now been pulled into Israel's
seven wars.
Six of those wars have led to bloodbaths
and disasters uh from Libya still in
civil war. Sudan unbelievably in two
civil wars because we broke the country
apart and each of those two parts now
has its own civil war. Somalia there's
not even a government. There is a
government actually very nice prime
minister that I know but uh barely
governance uh in in the country. Uh
Lebanon we see it's a invaded basically
destroyed country. Syria. Uh the US and
Israel worked for 15 years from Obama uh
until this past year to overthrow the
government. That was an active uh covert
regime change operation. Iraq, the 2003
war and the debacle that lasted uh for
years after that. And Iran was the last.
So, six of the seven places are in
chaos.
And from Israel's point of view, great.
We like chaos. That means we are the
military hegeimon for all of that region
stretching from Libya to Iraq. Chaos is
great. They they can't get their act
together. They're all in civil war. What
could be better?
The seventh is Iran.
And that's where we're facing right now.
And interestingly, when the war started,
Netanyahu tweeted, "This is my dream
come true
for 40 years." And I had to confess. I
made a mistake. I always said 30 years
cuz I dated it to Clean Break, 1996.
But I didn't know Netanyahu before he
was prime minister. I didn't know that
he had 10 years more of dreaming of this
war. So the offramp
violates
not only the American conditions of
defending its imperial strength, but the
Israeli dream of full control over the
region. And that's why the offramp is so
hard. I have to say one more thing just
because it is a little bit of a
complicated uh picture.
It's not incidental and I don't want
anyone to think I'm naive in this. When
we talk about why the United States
wants Iran within the US empire, why it
overthrew Mosedc in 1953
remember the oil. So I don't want to uh
forget to mention that that's not only a
1953 issue that brought that was aimed
to ensure that Iran would not take back
its oil from British and then American
interests. Trump absolutely without
question, no doubt, 100%
is as strongly beholden to the oil lobby
as he is to the Zionist lobby. And he
said so vividly, vocally in 2024. He
said, "Raise a billion dollars for me.
It's a deal. You'll get all the benefits
from this." what he did in Venezuela,
he thought he was about to do in Iran as
well. So, this needs to be understood as
just one more piece of this. Yes, he
wanted to fight with Iran for 46 years,
at least since 1980, probably 47, since
1979.
But what he thinks he learned from
kidnapping the Venezuelan president and
then suborning the Venezuelan government
is I can do a decapitation and then own
the oil of that country. And so part of
the motivation now was revenge. Bring
Iran back into the empire. But part of
the benefit of bringing Iran back into
the American Empire is you get the oil.
and he thought within one day he'll get
the oil because just like removing
Maduro
he thinks gave America Venezuela's oil
he thought killing the Iranian
governmental leadership starting with
this religious supreme leader and then
the top uh officials of the government
that were meeting that day with the
supreme leader he would take the oil. So
that's the tableau. This is why it's
hard to take the exit ramp because there
were reasons for this war to my mind.
Cruel, illegal, delusional. Uh so I
don't abide by any of those reasons, but
there were reasons for this war. And
taking the off-ramp means that none of
those would be fulfilled. From my point
of view, fine. None of them was valid.
But from the point of view of the two
architects of this war, Trump and
Netanyahu, that's quite hard to do. But
as I said, the alternative, which is an
escalated war within a few weeks, could
destroy the world economy
>> to uh Thank you for that. That was
Sorry to go on.
>> I loved it. I loved it. Um and it's much
needed because there's always a context.
You did this with the Ukraine war once
in this room and I've never stopped
thinking about it. Uh, thank you for
that. Couple quick follow-up questions.
You talked about the ongoing war against
Rome by the United States now 46 years
since 1980, first a proxy war with uh
Iraq, etc., etc. There are reports that
the United States in addition to all of
that has used geoengineering to evoke a
drought in Iran. Is that true?
I doubt it. There are enough reasons for
drought as a natural condition of uh a
an aid and semierid reason that we don't
have to go there.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. Um second
>> in fact I can tell you uh one uh one
visit to uh
uh I was in the Gulf region uh in Saudi
uh and then I went to Thran and in both
places this was many years ago now there
was already drought and it was it was
springtime and there were intense
sandstorms uh sandstorms like uh none of
us has ever experienced. if you haven't
cocktail or an evening
very nice on a uh you know a top floor
of an apartment building you couldn't
see anything out the window because it
was just completely darkened uh in the
afternoon by this sandstorm basically so
the point was uh it struck me then uh
these are aid regions Yes,
>> they are drying under the forces of
long-term changes that are underway and
having been in the Gulf and then in uh
Iran, it's of course exactly the same
ecosystem. It's the same environment.
It's the most natural thing that they
should be working together to solve
these problems. and you say this is
where do these lines of division come
from? Uh just because someone drew a
political line, it doesn't change the
fact that there's the sandstorm on one
side, the same sandstorm on the other
side, and they should be working
together. And so it just struck me. I'm
just re reminded of the fact that um I
had this intense
uh visceral feeling then how artificial
these political boundaries are because
this is a region uh and it's a region
that shares some very intense human
problems like how to get enough water to
stay alive dayto day and they should be
working together to solve that problem.
So I don't think in this case that you
need the United States to geoengineer
anything. I think it's happening by
itself. For decades, Russell Brand was
one of the most famous actors and
comedians and agnostics in the world.
Today he is one of the most sincere
Christians we know, a follower of
Christ. His personal transformation is
remarkable. We saw it up close. He has
now recounted it in an amazing book
called How to Become a Christian in
Seven Days. And it recounts what
happened to him. And it makes the case
to all of us for stepping away from our
secular assumptions and returning to the
only thing that matters, which is God.
I've read it. It's amazing. And right
now, there's only one place to get it.
Tucker Carlsonbooks.com.
This is the first release from our new
publishing company. We created Tucker
Carlson Books to bypass the sensors and
bring you things that are actually worth
reading and sharing. And we're starting
this venture with what matters most, and
that's Russell Brand's message of the
promise of forgiveness and joy through
Jesus. We're proud to launch our new
bookstore with Russell Brand's How to
Become a Christian in 7 Days. It is the
message this country needs most. Find it
today on tucker Carlsonbooks.com.
Second question, Clean Break 1996
um listed seven countries whose
governments need to be overthrown in
order to create room and strategic depth
and options for Israel. Six of those
wars have taken place. The US was and
well now seven, but the US was the
instrument of all of those. Correct.
Okay, great.
>> So this was Israel's plan, but the US
military was used. The US has spent5
to10 trillion dollars on this uh Israel
venture. This is the basic point. Uh
yes, we've had our own misguided ideas
about this, but um
it's just bizarre. Uh of course, Iraq,
we know in detail that this was a
concocted war. Uh but Syria has never
been uh understood in as much depth, but
it's the same story. Uh why suddenly did
Barack Obama feel the compulsion to task
the CIA with overthrowing Bashar
al-Assad?
>> Assad must go.
>> Yes.
>> That was on the lips of everyone in one
day.
>> Are you kidding? I remember I was on
Morning Joe uh that morning that either
Hillary or or
Obama said Saddam must go. And Joe
turned to me said, "What do you think
about that?" I said, "Oh, that's
interesting. How are they going to do
that?" Well, it took 14 years, hundreds
of thousands of deaths, tens of billions
of dollars, massive destruction, massive
destabilization. refugee crisis
>> to put a jihadist in in in charge right
now and then clean it up. But of course
>> to take a secular government that
protected religious minorities, aloites,
Christians, everybody
>> for generations generationally, father
and son did the same and replace it with
a guy we thought we were fighting
against. and to destroy, of course,
historic sites as they're doing in Iran
right now, cultural sites, I should say,
that are human heritage, not only Syrian
or Iranian heritage, but world heritage
because they've lasted thousands of
years and then our idiocy, we're
destroying them in in hours.
>> Yeah, I would say evil. But yeah, no,
that's um Okay, so I just want to be
clear with that. Third question um about
the offramp.
So the United States would have to the
president but the whole government would
have to swallow that. We'll just have to
admit it didn't work and Iran is now
more powerful. Iran is an economic power
which we didn't understand. I don't
think before this war we thought of them
as this emerging military threat. Turns
out they're an economic power cuz they
control the street. But from an Israeli
perspective
there is this process which I've seen
many times where people talk themselves
into believing their own rhetoric. So
you start out by saying the real threat
from Iran is its nuclear program, but
you don't mean it. You just want to take
Iran out because you don't want
Hezbollah and Hamas to hassle you. Got
it. But if you say it enough, you start
to believe that the main threat to your
existence is this government. And I
think the Israelis are there. Like I
think they believe that.
So could not just Netanyahu, the prime
minister, but the whole country, could
they live with a strengthened Iran or
would they be forced to do something
really radical?
Well, Netanyahu said a couple of days
ago that um they're out to annihilate
us, which is not true. Uh and
>> that's a heavy thing to say. And and it
shows uh I think a deep part of uh the
the psyche uh of Netanyahu personally
and of uh one strand of uh uh Israeli
extremism which is the belief and um it
is taught that uh they're out to
annihilate us uh every generation.
And um the uh Holocaust uh is used as
the model that um we uh can never uh uh
tolerate this again. So we must fight
preemptively against anyone that would
annihilate us. Well, it it leads to uh
as even Netanyahu said, a Sparta state,
a state that is just a war state.
They've lost the capacity for diplomacy
at all. Israel, unfortunately, has no
diplomacy.
It has diplomats, but the diplomats rip
up the UN charter or shred the UN
charter or stand in the podium of the UN
General Assembly and accuse the whole
world of anti-semitism and hatred and so
forth. It's not diplomacy at all because
uh one strand of thought is nobody can
be trusted. Uh we have to kill them
before they kill us. If you live like
that, you end up as a killer non-stop.
Uh and this is uh definitely one tragic
reality of uh the mentality of a
Netanyahu or others. He's been killing
before they kill us for decades. He's a
killer. He has become a non-stop killer.
He kills in the name of self-defense,
but he kills in the name of preemptive
self-defense.
And so, if you believe that the others
are out to kill you and you must not
talk to them and must not try to
understand or must not uh do anything
else, you end up as a non-stop killer.
Nao would say, "Oh, you're I don't know
if you what he would say to me, not not
much nice, but he would uh say you're
you're so naive." Uh and what I would
say to him is but you sir have the idea
not out of uh any reason but you have
the idea that you will have a greater
Israel and expunge the people uh that
live in your area that are not Israeli
Jews. That's your idea. Uh that for the
millions and millions of people there,
you will exterminate them or ethnically
cleanse them or rule over them. uh in
some racially segregated society and
then you want others to uh then when
others object to that you say that
they're out to destroy you. Why don't
you show that you have a human reason
that you have a human decency and say
that in conditions of peace there would
be a Palestine? Yes, of course. because
there are 8 million Palestinians
and in a situation of peace, we could
have calm uh with the rest of the region
without going to war, subverting
governments and so forth. But you don't
try to do that. Netanyao's position is
there's no possibility of diplomacy. We
must kill them before they kill us. But
without trying to have any
peace, without trying to understand that
there are legitimate, deep moral, legal,
and historical reasons for doing
something different from greater Israel
that kills, maims, destroys,
expropriates the Palestinian people and
claims territory seemingly wherever they
want in Lebanon or Syria and who knows
where else according to Ambassador
Huckabe. So I don't give
any credence to Netanyahu because his
starting point is not only fear but his
starting point is something obnoxious
which is we don't recognize
the people that live among us that we
have expropriated
that we have taken the land that we have
uh uh killed in by the tens of thousands
uh that we have denied basic political
rights and without that how can he think
that there could be some kind of uh
solution. So Netanyahu's absence of an
exit ramp starts from his own
radicalism. Not only from his fear, but
from a complete absence of diplomacy
that recognizes that there's another
side that needs to be dealt with as
human beings. And where that extremism
comes from is uh
I'm not sure. It's very pathological. uh
you could uh find it uh in some uh
religious extremist views that this is
our land. God gave it to us. It's nobody
else's and everyone else has to get the
hell out. I'm not sure exactly what
motivates it, but there's a complete
collapse of
understanding that there are people to
talk to that actually want to make
peace. So I always thought that it was
Netanyahu was leading this that he had a
particular worldview
um and that I don't know through his
brilliant political skill he was able to
control the country. Now it seems like
there are a lot of people who have even
more radical views and one of them would
be Danny Danon whom I know I always
thought was kind of a reasonable guy.
He's the Israeli ambassador to the
United Nations. There was an amazing
exchange between you and him at the UN
fairly recently that made me think, wow,
it's not just Netanyahu. Can you explain
that exchange?
>> Well, I can explain the exchange and I
can also say that there are uh two
variants of Israeli extremism that are
not the same, but they are now literally
a coalition. I mean, they're literally a
political coalition. uh and uh they are
a
a um ideological
uh coalition as well. So one is the view
every generation they're out to kill us.
We have to kill them before they kill
us. uh the preemptive strike, the clean
break idea, but again grounded in this
perverse
uh maybe related idea that there will
never be a Palestine alongside an
Israel, which is actually what led to
clean break, led to all these wars, led
to the militancy, was the absence of
Palestinian political rights alongside
Israeli political rights, the so-called
two-state solution. And since
Netanyahu's party lood going back to its
opening charter in 1977 said there will
never be a Palestinian state. Nothing to
talk about, no terms, no uh security
arrangements to make it possible. This
will all be Israel's sovereignty from
the Jordan River to the Mediterranean.
There was never a basis for a a
diplomatic way out within Israel from
Netanyahu's point of view. Now there's a
second variant in Israel which gives a
theological
interpretation of this. Uh Netanyahu's
interpretation is mainly security
and secular with the only theological
twinge being this uh idea that they're
always out to kill us every generation.
Uh and the Holocaust put that into
overdrive for completely understandable
reasons, but not rational reasons that
attend to current realities. So, I'd say
Netanyahu is the uh basically the
security vision, but again, to my mind,
irrational, cruel, illegal,
self-defeating, disastrous, not real
security for Israel, but security in the
phrase, we kill them before they kill
us. then is a very different variant
that is now the coalition partners
represented by two now well-known
leaders to us Ben Gavir and Smootrich
two cabinet ministers who are religious
religious with a very strange idea and
it's a new form of Judaism which uh
actually attaches to some ancient texts,
but was not a real form of Judaism for
2,000 years.
>> It's not what I grew up with at all.
>> It's not what I grew up with as a Jew at
all. Uh it's something absolutely
late 20th century, early 21st century.
One of the parties is called Jewish
power. Uh and it is uh the idea that
>> that's it actual name.
>> Yes.
uh in in Hebrew, yes. Uh we redeem
God's promise to us by becoming greater
Israel. So the act of this expanded
Israel is a religious
uh demand
upon us. This is our redemption is this
very political military program that we
have and that is Smootrich and Ben Gavir
uh which says on a religious basis we
couldn't have a state of Palestine next
door. God gave us that land. Uh that's
ours. That's part of the promised land.
that's not theirs. Even though
the Palestinian people were
living there for
well over a thousand years, probably
incidentally according to uh some uh
historical uh studies and
interpretations perhaps Jews who
converted to Islam uh in the 7th century
when Islam swept across uh the eastern
Mediterranean. Iranian and North Africa
uh in its foundational moments. Uh the
Islamic societies
the
Omayed and Abvisid caliphats uh enabled
Jews and Christians to live within uh
the Islamic lands to live peacefully and
to govern themselves primarily but to
pay a tax. uh and so as a way to a avoid
taxes many people converted we know this
uh and probably today's Palestinians
many of them are you know descendants
from across centuries of Jews who were
the settlers you know who were living
there
before the 7th century uh sweep of Islam
across the land that's a footnote even
David Benorian the so-called founder of
the state of Israel
held that view uh in the 1930s and 40s
calling the Palestinians really the
original Jews of the land who probably
converted and and became the
Palestinians but today
>> wait Bengurian said that
>> Bengorian said that yes
>> what was not to get sidetracked but
Bengurian was secular I think
>> yeah of course all of the original
Zionist
>> yes from Eastern Europe so what were I
don't understand
I know they wanted to leave Europe I get
But what was the justification in his
mind for displacing millions of people
from their land if he acknowledged that
they were the actual heirs of Abraham?
Yeah. The idea was uh
Jews are instead of a religion in their
view. The these were not religious
people by the way. They didn't consult
with the rabbis. So it's all very uh
ironic. But in their view Jews are not a
religion. uh they are a people and in
the ideology of Europe of the late 19th
century a people needs a state and um so
uh
the idea was there should be a Jewish
state that was the name of uh the
founder of Jewish Zionism Theodore
Herzel's first book the Jewish state
>> well that makes sense no but but but
>> but uh he asked so where and One option
was uh maybe what is today's Uganda.
>> Yep.
>> It it wasn't the Holy Land. It wasn't
some religious compulsion or a return to
uh this promised land in part and
ironically uh again very weird uh
twists. The rabbis had said
1500 years earlier, don't go back to the
Holy Land. Live where you are. Stay
peaceful. Someday a messiah will come
and there will be uh again the holy land
for us. But in the meantime, stay calm,
live where you are, behave and uh and uh
and uh obey God's laws. That was the
idea of the Jewish religion of the
rabbitic Jewish religion. So the variant
on display now that this is our land,
God promised to us. Uh we need to redeem
it. God will protect us is a new variant
that came in the 20th century with the
actual founding of the state of Israel.
It was not the original Zionist movement
which was almost completely secular. It
had a couple of rabbis which had some
modest influence. And then it especially
came after the 1967 war and the conquest
of uh the Palestinian territories then
and the occupation of them and the
beginning of the settler movements and
things became radicalized after that and
some radical rabbis and militant
militarist
violent uh violence preaching rabbis
like Mayor Kahani which was an an
American rabbi who preached violence uh
for the settler cause in Israel gained a
following and that group grew with the
illegal settlers in the occupied lands.
illegal because you're not allowed to
settle territory conquered in war
according to international law. And the
UN Security Council said repeatedly,
"No, you can't have settlers there." I
started visiting Israel myself uh 54
years ago. Uh, and when I first went in
1972,
uh, the, uh, first settlements were
taking place, and I was a high school
kid, so I didn't understand much of
anything, uh, but, uh, of what was going
on, but they told me this was making
facts on the ground so that this would
be ours. We would have our security and
so forth. Facts on the ground was the
the famous expression.
When I continued to go back uh in the
mid70s, the late 70s, suddenly there
were groups of young zealots dancing in
the streets of Jerusalem proclaiming
God's will about these settlements
because these were settlements in places
mentioned in the Bible. This was
suddenly now the redemption of God's
promise. This was something new. This
was not traditional Judaism. But I mean
traditional from 400 AD to to
1970.
I'm talking about uh about 1,600
years or so. This was something brand
new. It was a fervor. It was a zealatry.
It was a fundamentalism
that uh emerged that said this is ours.
No one can interfere with this. More
than that, it's God's command that we
control this land. It's not about
security. It's not about division. It's
not about where to draw lines. It's not
about treaties. It's God's command.
That's a big part of the Israeli
political scene right now. It's half the
the motivation and it's why all of this
is so radicalized and so zealous. But uh
as as we were talking um it's extremely
important in the US context to
understand the Christian Zionist
dimension to this because Zionism did
not originate with Judaism strangely or
with Jews I should say. uh Herzel was
encouraged in his Zionism by a Christian
Zionist
and Christian Zionism was an evangelical
belief that the Jews should go back to
make a homeland in the promised land or
the holy land. And that has roots
hundreds of years before these Jewish
secular Zionists started at the end of
the 19th century. And a big part of the
Christian Zionist movement started in
Britain in the first half of the 19th
century. These were Christians reading
the Bible and reading the Bible in very
particular ways. one may say
increasingly with an emphasis on the
last book of the Bible, Revelation. So
what's called esquetology or the end of
the world beliefs and part of that
esquetology preached by a British
preacher named Darby with a huge effect
subsequently in the United States was
that the Jews should go back to the Holy
Land
so that the second coming can occur
because the book of Revelations says
that the second coming of Christ will
occur. when the Jews are in control of
the Holy Land. It happens,
interestingly, that these Christian
Zionists were often
rather confirmed anti-semites
uh that wanted the Jews out of their own
country. They didn't want the Jews in
Britain. They didn't want Eastern
European Jews migrating to Britain and
so forth. So, they wanted them
conveniently anyway out of out of
Britain and back in the Holy Land. But
the point is
there is this uh there there is a uh set
of non-religious claims. Our security
depends on this. They're out to kill us.
We need dominance. Uh they're evil. Uh
they have nuclear weapons or they're
they want whatever. Those are all
security side. But then there's this
whole strong religious dimension. And
when you had the amazing interview with
uh with Ambassador Huckabe, which was I
think a world eyeopener, he
displayed in a way that people all over
the world had never seen before this
very particular
British and American Christian Zionism.
Uh it's
very particular. It's 19th and 20th
century. It's a very uh
specific way of reading a couple of
books of the three books of the Bible.
Uh I would say uh the uh Genesis uh the
promise of the land, the book of Joshua,
uh which says go kill everyone in the
land so you can take the land. Uh it's a
commandment strange in the Bible to
commit multiple genocides in the name of
God to get all the land that has been
promised to you. And then the book of
Revelation which is the final book of
the New Testament and it's a very very
particular reading. It's not at all
mainstream Judaism. It's not at all
mainstream Christianity anywhere in the
world. But it has its important
political uh base in the United States
and more traditionally in Britain. So
what we're seeing in Israel is an
extremism that is shocking. And now
coming back to my exchange with uh the
ambassador at the UN, I said to him that
I thought Israel was was and is
committing suicide. Uh,
I didn't accuse Israel of what it's
doing to others.
That's implicit perhaps in what I was
saying, but I said it's committing
suicide because it's taking such a
violent extremist course that it's
putting it outside
of the bounds of civilization, outside
of the bounds of uh opinion in all parts
of the world. putting it outside of
international law and relying entirely
on the United States to do that because
if Israel did this on its own, it would
be immediately suicidal. It wouldn't
stand for a day. It thinks the United
States is going to support this
extremism
on an unending, unconditional basis.
But you and I know that's not true.
Americans are sickened by this
extremism. They're sickened by uh the
tens of thousands of innocent deaths in
Gaza. They're disgusted with this war in
Iran. They're disgusted with the
trillions of dollars that the United
States has spent for Israel's clean
break. They're we're sick of it. Uh most
Americans are just sick of this right
now. overwhelmingly and the polls show
that. So I read analysis that says it's
going to take, you know, years and years
for America to reset its relationship
with Israel. I think that's absurd. If
our current system remains in place,
which was an open question, but if it
does, that's going to be abrupt. I mean,
people aren't going to get elected if
they're taking APAC money. We see nobody
supports what's going on right now. And
wait four weeks. If they don't choose
the off-ramp in the next few days, wait
a few weeks what it's going to be like
when their incomes are decimated, when
the world's economy is in a tail spin
because suddenly they realize in four
weeks half the Gulf has been blown to
pieces. What are they going to say then?
So, how is this going to be sustained
when just Americans basically don't want
to be the agents of mass murder and mass
suffering and most of us don't believe
that the mass expulsion of people is
somehow God's command. We don't believe
that.
>> Well, no. It's insane. And by the way,
from a Christian perspective, you can
only support Christian Zionism if you
ignore the Gospels, which are the heart
of Christianity. I mean, there's nothing
in nothing in there that supports it.
So, you would think, by the way,
the greatest
speech I know of is the sermon on the
mount.
>> It's unbelievable
>> for everybody, for the whole world. This
isn't a matter of who believes,
>> but blessed are the peacemakers,
>> of course,
>> should resonate. I think it does
resonate with people all over the world.
The message of Jesus in the s in the
sermon of the mount is completely the
opposite of what we're doing right now.
And that is not from a Christian or
Jewish or any other. That's from a human
perspective cuz he was speaking about
humanity about what is decent for human
beings about how human beings should
treat other people. They should not kill
them. They should not make strangers out
of them. The good Samaritan was the one
that rescued the man on the side of the
road. The Samaritan who was the
outsider, he's teaching us something.
And the part that I love about the
teaching that I think is so important is
why do you point to the moat in the
other's eye when you have the plank in
your own eye? And what Jesus is saying
very clearly, don't be a hypocrite. Yes.
>> And don't just say they're evil without
reflecting on yourself. This is so
basic. All of that is left out because
this new version
of Judaism or of Christian Zionism is
one chapter of Genesis or maybe two.
chapter 15 and chapter 18, God's
promise, the book of Joshua, which is
probably a political tract written
during the late 7th century BC during
the reign of King Josiah of the state of
Judah as a political tract that says,
"Murder other people to take the
promised land." And then the book of
Revelation, the gospels are not part of
that text. No. And it's clear that
they're not because the message of the
gospels is completely different.
>> Yeah. Jesus is saying, "You've been told
don't murder. I tell you, don't even be
angry at at someone else." It's a it's a
message of radical reconciliation and
nonviolence. So that's just what it
says. I mean, it's inconvenient, but
it's true.
So I guess my question is though, if the
United States withdraws under popular
pressure, its unconditional support for
Israel and the Iranian regime stays in
place, some form of it does, and once
again, Iran is more powerful than it's
ever been and now has a clear incentive
to buy a nuke from Pakistan or somewhere
else. Those are like like what does
Israel do at that point? That's my
concern cuz now it's kind of out of
options.
>> Yeah. So here's what I think. First of
all, we should look at uh Iranian um
invasions of other countries. As I said,
it hasn't happened for 230 years. If I
have the uh the arithmetic right, as far
as I know, uh the the last uh
actual military operation of Persia or
Iran uh was against Basra in the 1790s.
Uh
Iran is not out to destroy Israel. Iran
does not want to be destroyed by a uh a
petulant uh annoyed American empire from
which it escaped. This is the most basic
point and if you've dealt with Iranians
for decades as I have, that message is
absolutely clear. So, Israel is not
at threat from Iran. It is not a threat
from Iran. This is the basic point. Iran
wants its place in the world. It doesn't
want to be bombed and destroyed by
Israel and the United States. This is
the first most important point.
Second,
Iran has supported
Hezbollah and Hamas
and it would stop supporting
Hamas and Hezbollah
if there is a Palestinian state
alongside the state of Israel. This is
the most basic point. You want a path to
peace, you make peace. And the way to
peace is there are two peoples in that
land. Uh when it started there were 90%
uh Palestinian Arabs. Now it's roughly
half and half between Israeli Jews and
Palestinian Arabs, but there need to be
two states. Or I'm fine if there's one
democratic state, but Israel doesn't
want that for sure. So two states, but
there can't be one state in which Israel
rules over everybody or kills the others
or expropriates the others, that's
what's not possible. But if there is a
political settlement within Israel,
then there will be an end of the
militancy as well. And this is a
fundamental point. Iran does not want to
live as a militant state. I know it
because I watch and I discuss for
decades. It wants to live though, not as
an American satrappy. So the idea that
if we leave Iran is just overpowering
and they're going to defeat Israel and
so forth. No, there. First of all,
first of all, Israel will not be
defeated. It has nuclear weapons. It
would use them. Iran does not have
nuclear weapons. It actually doesn't
want nuclear weapons. If we had the
slightest sanity, honesty, and
rationality in the world, it would be
the easiest thing in the world to make
sure that Iran has no nuclear weapons
cuz they don't want them. And the first
thing, just in digression, that you
would do if you wanted to make sure that
Iran doesn't have nuclear weapons, you
would not kill the religious leader who
issued the decree that nuclear weapons
are against the religion. But the first
thing they did was to kill the very
religious leader that issued the
so-called fatwa to uh prohibit nuclear
weapons. So, Israel,
the idea that it's in dire threat if we
leave is wrong. We also need to remember
there's a whole world out there. We
don't like to admit that it's not the
American way, but there's Russia,
there's China, there's India, there's
Brazil, there I'm mentioning countries
in the so-called bricks. They will tell
Iran,
"No,
now you have peace. Now you live
peacefully."
So Iran cannot
engage in some regional
takeover to become the super regional
power because they're also profoundly
constrained right now. They're trying to
stop themselves from being destroyed by
American bombs. Precisely what Trump has
threatened repeatedly, the end of their
civilization, which by the way is 5,000
years old, two 20 times longer than the
United States. Okay? So, they're not
about to do
all these terrible things. They're not
about to hold a chokehold over the world
economy. President Xi Jinping, who has,
let's just say, a lot of influence with
Iran, uh, as a main consumer and
supplier and trader and many, many other
things said yesterday, the straits of
Hormuz need to be opened.
Need to be open.
Iran is not going to do all these
horrible things that are imagined. And
when I say leave,
it wouldn't hurt to leave also with an
agreement.
Okay, we're leaving. You don't invade.
We're not invading you. Israel. There's
going to be a Palestinian state
alongside uh Israel as is the core of
international law since 1967 indeed
since 1940
uh47.
Uh and um you'll live peacefully.
They'll live peacefully and uh you won't
have nuclear weapons. you'll go under
IAEA
inspection according to the terms of the
nuclear non-prololiferation treaty which
by the way Israel doesn't abide by of
course at all so it's already asymmetric
but Iran has said okay we'll do it
asymmetrically but put us under this
don't put us under the bombs so all I'm
saying is there's no sense in which the
exit ramp means Iran becomes
the great threat to Israel and the
dominant threat. But what it does mean
and I think this is really the
fundamental point here. I have to say
greater Israel is an untenable project.
This is the most basic point. If you
believe
Mike Huckabe
then what I'm saying is not acceptable.
If you believe that Israel should
control all of this land should
and if you take uh Israel's leadership
uh that they will I would still advise
Donald Trump don't fall for it. It's a
$10 trillion
disaster for the United States. Not the
least in America's interest. Stay out of
it. Stay clear of it. It's a
Netanyahu is a repeated failure and liar
and everything he's told us for 30 years
has turned out to be the opposite. So
I'd say that anyway from our point of
view. But yes, if you believe that your
purpose is uh greater Israel and
continued expansion of Israel's borders,
then what I'm saying, no, you you
wouldn't accept it. You say, why should
we settle for that? But I don't believe
that. I believe in peace. I believe in a
secure state of Israel. I believe in a
secure state of Palestine. I believe in
getting on with our lives and not
focusing America's
resources, squandering them endlessly
for decades in this absolutely
delusional Israeli cause of greater
Israel. It's absurd. It's tragic. It's
got to end. And it needs to end now
before we have a complete disaster.
>> Can it can Trump constrain control
Netanyahu?
>> Of course. The question is, can Trump
constrain himself? Uh, can he say just
ending this, I thought it was going to
be a one-day Maduro type operation.
That's what BB told me. BB was
bullshitting me. Uh, now I understand
it. It didn't work. I'm stopping this
and I'm telling BB, you stop this, too.
Um, and could that work? Well, when
Trump said to Netanyahu, stop stop the
bombing of Beirut, we had a
demonstration, it can work. Could Israel
continue the war without the United
States? Basically, not for one day.
Could Israel uh actually survive the
global approprium including the American
approprium of Israel's extremism? I
don't think for one day actually Israel
needs to trade. It needs tourism. It
needs contracts. It needs finance. And
if Israel's totally completely a rogue
state without the American Empire
backing it, without the American
military backing it, without the
American intelligence, uh without uh the
uh uh the uh satellite data coming in,
it's not Israel's, it's America's.
Believe me, uh without all of that, no,
Israel cannot do anything on this. But
we bought into the whole package. We
bought into it for a mix of perceived
American self-interest in our global
power. That is Israel's hijgemony in the
region was consistent with our desire
for global control. We bought into the
Iran story because Israel's story that
we got to kill them before they kill us
is not inconsistent with our desire to
have revenge and to control their oil.
In other words, it's a partnership. Y
and uh it's a real partnership. But
Israel's
capacity
to have this uh uh
war that stretches now from Libya to
Iran. That's an American capacity, but
we're bleeding from it. We're bleeding
from Israel's wars. And this, I think,
is really important to understand. You
know, Trump said something quite
interesting. the Washington gaff,
meaning that he told the truth. Uh, not
off script, but he said, "We can't
afford the wars and those things like
child care, Medicare, and Medicaid, and
other those individual things," he said.
And you know what? It's true. We're
bleeding. And what did he do? He said,
"Okay, we're going to cut all those
things that Americans actually need and
want because we want our health care. We
actually want to be able to have uh
dental repairs or get medicines or see a
doctor or have an operation uh if our
lives depend on we we want that." And
Trump said, "No, we have to have war
instead."
So he put in a budget a couple of weeks
ago which didn't get any attention
because it won't be enacted by Congress,
but he put in a budget in which the
military spending goes up another half a
trillion dollars and the things like he
said, you know, the health and other
things, oh we can't afford that, goes
down in this budget to make people who
are hurting in this country,
they would hurt desperately more. Not to
mention the gas pump and not to mention
uh everything food prices and everything
else that they are already facing from
these wars, but will face
cataclysmically
if they don't choose the off-ramp.
So,
can Trump say this? He has to say this
for the American people. First of all,
he has to because this is really about
us right now. He has to listen to the
American people. We don't want this.
It's no good for us. It's anyway crazy
extremism. We don't buy into this. We
don't buy into the story. We don't need
this. We don't need the American Empire
owning Iran. We don't need revenge for
1979.
We don't need greater Israel. We don't
need all of these things. We need our
health care, our dental care, our daily
lives. We want peace. We don't want to
be murdering school girls. We don't want
to be murdering uh people. We don't want
to be destroying
ancient cultures in different places in
the world. And Mr. President,
your partner cannot do this
for one moment without your backing.
So your job is to tell
Mr. Netanyahu
your your clean break, 30 years, maybe
10 trillion dollars of American treasure
now piled up in debt.
We tried your approach. It's done. Now
we're going to try peace. That's what he
needs to tell him. It can work. If he
doesn't do that and in the next few
days, uh, you know, this accelerates,
and you've said if it does accelerate,
Iran's first move will be to destroy
civilian infrastructure in the Gulf,
uh, Del Energy, the rest. What are the
effects at that point? Like what are the
Let's just start with the economic
effects.
by the rest of the world. Yeah.
Strangely enough, I came into my
profession, which I've been a professor
at universities for 46 years and advised
well over a 100 governments around the
world. I came into this profession
writing my PhD dissertation on the oil
shocks of the 1970s. I wrote the first
model of what uh how they worked, why
they had such negative effects
>> after 73 after 73 and 79. So uh I wrote
the book literally and it's published in
uh 1982 called the economics of
worldwide stagflation.
The results of those two oil shocks give
us an idea of what would happen. uh what
happened in 1973-74
when there was an oil embargo and then
in 1979 80 when there was the Iranian
revolution was a big disruption of oil
supplies. It sent oil prices soaring and
it sent the world economy into a tail
spin and it was a very uh particular
kind of tail spin because people lost
their jobs, incomes went down uh and
inflation soared at the same time. And
so you had a economic downturn and a
rise of inflation which at the time was
viewed as a paradox because usually you
have a recession and the prices come
down or you have a boom and the prices
accelerate. But this was a contraction
and an inflation.
>> So people had less money coming in and
everything costs more to buy.
>> That's it. And that's what was called
stagflation.
Now the difference of then and now is
that the two shocks then were
temporary
stops of the flows of oil. One was a
boycott by the Arab countries against
the US and other buyers like shutting
down the straightforward.
>> Just to be clear, what were they mad
about?
>> They they were mad about this the uh uh
1973 war
>> US support for Israel. Exactly.
>> Just to be clear, this goes this has
been the same issue.
>> I was four years old when that happened.
>> This this was this goes back a long way.
And then 197980 was the Iranian
revolution. Um and uh
they were the the oil got turned off but
the oil fields weren't destroyed. There
was no war in the oil fields. There was
no physical destruction of
infrastructure. Refineries weren't
destroyed. What will happen in the next
few weeks if we don't choose the
off-ramp is the physical destruction of
a lot of the Gulf region and of the
Middle East more generally because the
US will rain missiles and bombs on uh
Iran and Iran will launch what it has
against targets in the neighborhood to
show deterrence.
and hoping that that deterrence will
stop something. Often instead what you
get is just both sides unleashing their
arsenals.
And what will happen in a short period
of time is not a closure of shipping but
a destruction of the physical capacities
of providing the oil and the gas and the
fertilizers uh and the prochemicals and
the other uh
very core commodities for the world
economy. And it doesn't take that much
to bring the world economy into a tail
spin because uh you don't need to close
down half the oil supply. uh you might
need to uh shut off uh 20% of the world
oil supply and that by enough will send
the prices soaring
make Americans really suffer across the
board because it's not only at the gas
pump and not only in the utility bills
but also in the cost of food which will
soar from this as well because there
will be a worldwide disruption of food
supplies coming from this because we're
a very significant proportion of the ura
which underpins the nitrogenbased
fertilizers of the world come from this
region
>> from natural gas
>> from from the natural gas production.
Exactly. from from the oil and gas um
fields, the the hydrocarbon production
and other prochemicals as well. I I'm
afraid that it won't take long for this
to happen. And
>> fall if that happens globally.
>> Yes. One one leader uh pulled me aside a
few weeks ago. I don't want to say who
exactly but said um that uh that person
was in a uh in a uh a country that has a
lot of oil production not not from the
region and said Jeffoff you don't
understand I governed our state oil
company
>> these are complex systems they don't get
rebuilt so fast believe me right this
was a very authoritative figure and um I
really take that to heart.
>> Well, energy extraction, refining,
petrochemicals, distribution, it's all
about a million times more complicated
than people understand.
>> Exactly. And these are very
sophisticated plants and they are not
built for war. They are built for just
normal, peaceful, complex, sophisticated
operations. And a lot of that could be
destroyed in a very very short period of
time.
>> No, I I appreciate that. And I think the
view in the US seems to be like if
there's oil under the ground, you stick
a straw in, it comes out, then
>> it's if you ever if you go and tour a
petrochemical plant or oil refinery or
any extraction facility, I mean it is
like highest level technology, smartest
people, super hard to understand the
market.
>> I'll tell you, we had uh you know, one
of a place you know well and I know
well, one of the most sophisticated
places in the planet uh the the
Emirates.
>> Yes. uh asking uh the Federal Reserve a
few days ago for emergency swap lines
that may be needed in the event of a
crisis. This is kind of shocking because
uh first of all, the Emirates you think
of as super rich.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh it's the uh it's the place where rich
people go to put their money uh in the
region. Of course, it's completely
destabilized by all of this. It's a
complete disaster for them what's
happened. But they are girding for the
downstream effects of what I'm talking
about which is that first you get the
physical destruction then you get the
real economy so-called the actual
physical production of industrial
products of uh employment in the
manufacturing sector and cascading
across the economy having huge uh
negative consequences. But then you get
the financial effects because people
say, "Is this place viable anymore? I'm
I'm withdrawing my money." But the the
Emirates operates on a USbacked dollar
standard. And suddenly you have a run on
your banks. You have a run on your
financial markets. So they're already
asking, can we have emergency lines of
credit? And maybe yes, maybe no. But
that's the tip of the iceberg of the
financial consequences that can come
from all of this. So you get a huge
cascade of effects. And then I want to
mention because I want to mention for
completeness um it's more speculative
but the daily evidence is growing that
the
what we call the intraanual phenomenon
of uh ENSO which is fluctuations in uh
air pressure and uh currents in the uh
or sea surface temperatures in the
Pacific which cause Elinos.
which people know about and leninas.
It looks like a very large maybe what
they're calling a super El Nino is
building for later this year and it may
not happen but the evidence is growing
that it seems like that's the case. So
people might be curious what does that
mean? It means that warm surface water
over the Pacific would spread to
basically the west coast of South
America. When you get a very powerful El
Nino,
the temperatures and rainfall patterns
and drought patterns and storm patterns
in all of the tropical and subtropical
regions of the world are hard hit. One
of the things for example that happened
in the 197374
oil shock was that there was also an El
Nino that year. It just I'm remembering
uh and it was the combination that sent
food prices soaring worldwide. Uh, and
if we have that dual combination, I've
been saying to myself for years, the
next big El Nino or super El Nino is by
itself going to be world destabilizing
because there are a lot of countries on
the edge right now, on the edge
financially, on the edge socially. Uh
the world's an unstable place because
it's been so perturbed by everything
that's happened in in the last years
that many places are just on the edge of
solvency in their governments or
financial stability and so forth. But if
you combine a mass uh destruction in
West Asia, the Gulf, the Eastern
Mediterranean,
uh with a super El Nino, I don't even
know. Somebody's going to have to write
the next book quickly about this because
we would not have had a shock like that
since World War II. Certainly. and the
effects on political destabilization
uh on the effects of uh governments
falling the potential cascading of this
war would be tremendous and
uncontrollable.
Just think in addition to everything
else uh a uh naval fleet from China is
heading towards the Gulf right now. It's
heading towards the Gulf to escort
Chinese vessels or uh I don't know if
it's only Chinese flagged or chi vessels
heading to China uh to give them
military escort.
Suppose there's a war going on. Suppose
the United States says we have a
blockade and we interdict uh a Chinese
vessel. Suppose that a Chinese destroyer
comes alongside
You know, we're not in self-control
right now. Uh sailors are not in
self-control. Captains are not in
self-control. Uh we're living uh at uh
at at uh nanocond speed. Maybe uh
Palunteer's uh Maven system will say
shoot. Uh, who knows what will happen,
but we're just lighting fuses
that could blow up everything if we
choose the ramp of escalation. And I
think it will go faster than we imagine
and without control. We don't seem to
have any real control in our government
right now even of basic processes. We
don't have inter agency reviews. We
don't have expert intelligence that are
guiding policy. We don't have anything
that is systematic.
I think in Israel it's the same way. uh
when you have a cascade of crisis, when
missiles are at hypersonic speed and
you're making decisions uh at uh you
know with the a few seconds warning or
uh a minute or two warning of incoming
missiles. Oh,
what are we doing with all of this
gamble when the whole premise of this
war was wrong and when the tactical
premise that this was a one-day
operation
was proved wrong by the second day? Why
are we still facing this possibility of
complete disaster?
And I have to say, I'm sorry to say it,
Tucker, but um
Every few days I get an email from
somebody who says, um, I really
appreciate what you say, Professor Saxs,
but I do want you to know that we're in
the end times. Uh, and, uh, that this is
all, uh, as prophecied. Um, and so,
thank you for your voice. They're not
hostile messages. They're very nice,
sweet people, uh, who say we're in the
end times. I I'm hoping we're not in the
end times. This is the basic point. We
should have some prudence.
Somebody should reach the president of
the United States and say stop before
disaster.
>> I've tried. I wonder what do you what do
you make of that? What do you make of I
know you're you're not a famously
observant man.
However, things are happening that
certainly don't have any precedent in
our lifetime. I mean, you've watched the
world carefully for 50 years, and all of
a sudden, anomalous things are happening
all over. People are behaving in ways
you you never would have expected they
behave.
>> Do you allow for the possibility that
some of this is pre-ordained that like
there's that, you know, getting off the
train?
>> I don't uh I've studied history now for
uh my whole life and I've seen um
disasters. Uh, I've studied intensively
disasters and near misses and avoided
disasters
uh with care. I wrote a book about the
Cuban Missile Crisis and its aftermath.
I've studied World War I and World War
II upside down, right side up from every
country's perspective. I've spent a half
century uh looking at this. Terrible
things happen because individual
leaders and governments make
miscalculations.
They don't talk to each other. Uh they
don't understand the ramifications.
They have a breakdown of uh systematic
processes.
Um, so I don't think that this is
ordained, but I think we're close to
overload right now, which is what you
see happening around crisis often.
>> What What does it mean overload?
>> It it means that um very
consequent decisions need to be made
skillfully
and the the decisions are a big deal.
They have a very very large consequence.
uh I would call them uh nonlinearities
meaning it's uh that that the
consequence of the choice uh can take us
into disaster or into uh
into solution. So in other words, these
are really big choices
and um
the truth is individuals make a big
difference at times like this. Um
what we've seen, what I've tried to
understand, you know better than I do,
but I'm trying to understand the
decision process in the US government
right now. Normally you would have uh a
a deliberative process. Uh we know
process that I've studied very carefully
as have many many scholars uh the Cuban
missile crisis. Uh President Kennedy uh
immediately installed an executive
committee XCOM and uh during the 13 days
of the Cuban missile crisis they met
repeatedly they debated. They discussed
options. It was all put on tape. It's
all been studied for decades later. Many
of the judgments that were made were
very wrong. President, and one of the
lessons, by the way, of the Cuban
Missile Crisis was that it was President
Kennedy's cool and rationality and
decency that saved the world actually.
Um quite a remarkable truth because many
hotheads uh and many hotheads in senior
military positions especially Curtis
Lameé said no go blow up the commies
let's go to nuclear war uh and almost to
the point of uh insubordination
uh lame was pressing Kennedy uh to
launch attacks and basically
accusing Kennedy of uh you know not not
uh being uh not not standing up uh
properly for America. Kennedy did save
the world but what it showed was a mix
of
very detailed deliberation
back channels that were extremely
important. for example then the UN
secretary general Utant played a huge
role as an intermediary and um good
judgment of the leader today I can't see
any process uh what we hear from outside
accounts and again you know better than
I but what we read is that this was
Trump's decision basically yes led by
Netanyahu
>> that's correct
>> okay Netanyahu has an agenda. His
agenda, in my mind, is uh fanatical
and wrong and has been mistaken for 30
years and has cost America a fortune.
It's just been wrong. I think the man is
a disaster. I think he has the wrong
framework of the world, just a wrong
understanding. Uh, of course he also has
his incentives for his job and
everything else. I'm talking about his
understanding of the world and um Trump
bought into that. Normally there would
be the National Security Council with
detailed inter agency assessments. There
would be the uh uh national intelligence
agencies reporting. uh our friend Tulsi
Gabbard, the head of uh the director of
national intelligence would be weighing
in
heavily. The joint chiefs of staff would
be explaining doubts which they clearly
had. There would be consultations with
senior members of Congress. That was
routine. in the Cuban missile crisis.
The president of the United States
consulted with the leaders of Congress
in detail. By the way, even though this
was an emergency commander-in-chief,
yes, but he knew there was a branch of
Congress that was essential for uh this.
I don't see any
such decision making taking place right
now and
this is absolutely dangerous. Uh
actually uh
the president of the United States needs
to get real analysis, data,
intelligence,
internal debate, opposition
and uh the president has uh ultimate
decisions on many things. Not on
everything, but on many things, but not
on the basis of a gut, not on the basis
of a whim, not on the basis of I believe
that Iran is like Venezuela, which I
think was part of the idea, not on the
basis of Netanyahu
spinning some absurd yarn or Mossad
spinning some absurd yarn to one person
with a group of sick offense listening
in and saying, "Well, I don't know. It
looks doubtful, but I will follow you,
Mr. President." That is not the kind of
deliberative process that keeps us in
safety.
>> And yet, I think that's exactly the
process. I don't think there's any
decision maker or even uh anyone who
influences the decisions greatly other
than Trump. I think uh the degradation
of our political system is so uh deep
right now that uh maybe there is no u
no chance for that. But I do every day
plead with the congressional leaders to
do their constitutional duty because
they're not doing it right now.
>> I know. uh and it's not uh you know be
good and go tell Trump they're a
co-equal branch of government that under
article one of the constitution assigns
them the responsibility for war for the
declaration of war it's not even shared
they are the only branch that can
declare war and when
I don't know how many een times now the
Republicans
All but one,
all but the best Republican senator by
far, Ran Paul. I regard him as the best
senator in in the whole Senate. Uh,
and all the Democrats on the other side,
but one, John Federman, who I regard as
u weird uh in his complete total
allegiance to Israel's reckless agenda.
um vote that Congress should not have
any oversight over this war completely
contrary to the whole framework of the
Constitution.
It shows how degraded we have become.
>> Maybe it's an inevitable process where
you know in late stage republics like
ours all power vests in the executive
the legislative body. Well, think of it
this way since you know so many world
leaders. Is there any legislative body
in any country you're familiar with that
has become more powerful
in the last 10 years or they're all
shrinking in authority? It's
>> I know lots of places that have
very high levels of deliberation.
>> Yep.
>> Very rational processes. By the way,
people will be very surprised to hear me
say it and they'll doubt it and they
won't believe it. But China has
among the most deliberative processes
that I see in any government in the
world because we portray, you know, Xi
Jinping is the as as the leader who
decides everything. I I was just in
Beijing a couple of weeks ago and
they've just announced a very very
sophisticated
economic program. Um, and I spoke to
many people that were part of it. It was
two years of detailed deliberation over
cutting edge sectors and what to do and
how to uh combine public and private
initiatives. Very sophisticated.
We don't have that right now. So this is
quite strange. We have just the
opposite. But I wonder do you think that
our big picture asking a lot to predict
something like this but that our current
system survives this moment?
We have one uh overwhelming delusion
that is held firmly by a president who
has his own personal delusions. And that
is that America
reigns supreme in the world. And every
day when President Trump says we are the
most powerful blah blah blah blah blah
in the history of the world,
this is a
of course he feels good saying this. Of
course maybe his followers feel good
saying this, but it's a it it's
completely totally the wrong approach to
our world right now.
The serious part of our world is the
world faces many deep challenges. There
are many nuclear armed countries. There
are many powerful countries. We need to
find a way to get along, to understand
each other, to cooperate, to solve
problems, and to avoid the traps of a
war that can destroy the world economy
or even the world in a short period of
time. So all the bluster
is a remnant of the idea that the US has
pursued during its imperial
era since World War II that we should
run the world. And Trump has a
particular view of that which is that he
should run the world. And so
we have a a workable system. It's
actually worked quite brilliantly at
times. It's a pretty complicated
machinery. Uh it it could be updated in
some pretty useful ways. But I used to
work uh for some years in internship
positions in the Congress in the 1970s.
And Congress actually worked as an
institution. for example, it held
hearings, it wrote papers, it proposed
legislation, it actually did things. Uh
there were leaders uh
uh Fulbright and others who spoke out
and wrote brilliant books and did all
sorts of wonderful things and uh I met
many of them as a kid. Uh and that idea
that there was a legislative branch
where you would have lions of the Senate
and the House of Representatives and a
speaker who would be a independent uh
voice of uh politics as the people's
tribune. It actually worked to an
extent. It really did. I was there. I
watched it. I saw it. I quite loved it.
Uh we don't have that right now. So
could it could it work? Yes. Uh I think
there are many interesting things to do
in our digital age. We can get people
involved much more. We can have public
deliberations in different ways. We can
upgrade update the way that our system
works. But yes, the system could work.
It doesn't have to dissolve or devolve
to one person operating on gut hunches
uh based on delusions of grandeur
that could send the world to disaster.
That doesn't have to be the way the
world and our system works
>> or ends.
>> Or ends. Exactly. Thank you,
>> Jeffrey Sax. Thank you very much for
that.
>> Great to be with you, Tucker. Thanks.